On the night of the 20th of January 1936, just
before midnight, King George V of the United
Kingdom died at Sandringham House. His eldest son
was present in the royal residence and immediately
succeeded him as King Edward VIII. The following
morning, Edward broke with royal protocol by
being present at St James’ Palace to watch from a
balcony as the proclamation of his own accession
as king was read out to the nation. Previous
monarchs had not done this. It was the first
small sign that Edward would refuse to adhere to
the basic rules of the monarchy. An even greater
problem though, was the woman by his side on the
21st of January 1936. This was Wallis Simpson,
a twice-married American divorcee whom Edward was
in a relationship with. Over the next two years,
Edward’s love life and his inflammatory behaviour
would lead to him losing his throne and then
entering into a highly controversial tour of
Nazi Germany where he met with the likes of Adolf
Hitler, Hermann Goring and Joseph Goebbels. All
the while, Wallis Simpson was by his side after
they finally married each other on the 3rd of
June 1937 in France. Why did Edward have to give
up his throne for Wallis? Were he and his wife
traitors who engaged in talks with the Nazis about
restoring Edward to the throne in Britain? This is
the story of King Edward VIII and Wallis Simpson,
the king who abdicated and the woman
for whom he gave up his throne.
The man known to history as King Edward VIII
of the United Kingdom and Emperor of India
was born on the 23rd of June 1894 at White
Lodge, Richmond Park in Surrey, England.
His father was George, the eldest son of Edward,
Prince of Wales, the son and heir of Queen
Victoria of Britain.
As Victoria was into her mid-seventies by
the time young Edward was born in 1894, it
was clear that her son, the future Edward
VII, Prince of Wales, and Edward’s grandfather,
would soon succeed her.
That would place the young Edward as second
in line to the throne when it occurred, which
it soon did when Victoria died in January
1901.
Young Edward’s mother was Mary of Teck,
the daughter of the Duke of Teck, a senior
German.
Between them George
and Mary had six children,
five boys and one girl.
Edward was the eldest, but
nearly as consequential
as the years went by was the next eldest child,
a boy named Albert after his great-grandfather,
Victoria’s long deceased husband over who’s
death she had never fully recovered.
Edward’s full name was Edward Albert Christian
George Andrew Patrick David and during his
youth he was always referred to within the
family as David.
Edward was raised from his very youngest years
as a future king.
He would, no doubt, not ascend to the throne
for several decades, but accidental deaths
and illnesses had created a situation where
a person in line to the throne in the way
Edward was could sometimes ascend at a very
young age.
His parents were aloof and somewhat gruff
in their parenting methods, but it was not
a wholly unhappy household, though Edward
grew to become wary of his father’s angry
outbursts about relatively unimportant issues.
He later stated in his memoirs that he felt
unloved and his childhood experiences seem
to have inculcated in him a desire to avoid
having children in later life, which he never
would.
More broadly, Edward became known for having
an easy charm in his younger years, which
allowed him to mix freely with members of
different classes, though his intellect was
hardly prodigious.
In these younger years he and his siblings
were largely educated at home at York Cottage
at Sandringham and at Frogmore near Windsor
Castle.
As he entered his teenage years Prince Edward
was sent to the naval college at Osborne on
the Isle of Wight.
From there he progressed through to the Royal
Naval College and then on to serve on HMS
Britannia.
This was a virtually identical training to
that which his father had undertaken in his
younger years and which indeed has remained
a staple of royal princes ever since.
Despite being an heir to the throne, Edward
was not overly protected and experienced some
bullying in his youth in the navy.
Otherwise, his upbringing was somewhat limited.
He was not trained to develop his mind or
become a significant scholar in the same way
in which his forebears in the seventeenth
or eighteenth centuries might have been.
As a result he grew up with an intellectually
limited worldview.
This limited intellectual development was
all the more concerning when in May 1910,
with the death of his grandfather, his father
became King and so Edward became heir to the
throne at the age of fifteen.
According to tradition, he was soon given
the title of Prince of Wales and despite still
being a teenager was quickly drawn into public
life.
The occasional appearances at public events
were interspersed throughout the early 1910s
with studies at the University of Oxford which
his father had decided Edward should attend.
However, Edward proved an indifferent student
and when turmoil struck Europe towards the
end of his time there he was
glad of the distraction.
In the summer of 1914 war descended across
Europe.
It had been brewing for decades as the rise
of a united Germany in the
1870s had destabilised
the balance of power in Central Europe and
created a major rival to Britain.
Other issues such as rivalry for colonial
possessions in Africa and fervent nationalist
sentiment in the Balkans, where the Empire
of Austria-Hungary and the Russian Empire
were rivals to secure control over the collapsing
Ottoman Empire, had compounded matters.
In the end it was a regional crisis here in
the summer of 1914, the assassination of the
heir to the Austro-Hungarian Empire, Archduke
Franz Ferdinand, by a Serb nationalist, which
lit the match that ignited the war.
In the final days of July and the first week
of August Britain, France and Russia went
to war with Germany and the Austro-Hungarian
Empire.
The major front for the British for the duration
of what soon became known as the First World
War was in northern France where the British
and French were soon bogged down in attritional
trench warfare with the Germans.
As part of the effort by the royal family
to show solidarity with the millions of British
men who were now being conscripted into the
military and sent to fight in France, Prince
Edward and others were assigned to serve as
officers in the army.
Edward was commissioned into the Grenadier
Guards in the last days of July 1914 and took
to military service very well, finding that
he enjoyed the camaraderie in ways which his
studies had not fulfilled him.
However, his wartime experience can hardly
be said to have been authentic.
Neither Edward, nor any other senior members
of the royal family or major noble lines could
be placed in harm’s way, where they might
be captured or killed.
As such for much of the next four years he
was effectively chaperoned
by his fellow soldiers
in roles across northern France.
Some of these were tokenistic, such as when
he was sent as a sort of royal ambassador
to meet with French generals, but when he
appeared to inspect British army camps on
the Western Front it is understood to have
genuinely improved morale on the front.
Here was a prince and a member of the royal
family actively showing up to do his own
military
service.
Indeed, on one or two occasions, despite the
extensive precautions taken, Edward did find
himself in danger during the war, notably
when his chauffeur was killed by exploding
artillery and his car crashed in northern
France.
Moreover, his range of activities extended
beyond France, with a visit to the Middle
East in 1916 to meet and greet Britain’s
Australian and New Zealander allies.
The war was significant in one other way which
would have a small implication for Edward
and his family for decades to come.
At the outset of the conflict the royal family
was known as the House of Saxe-Coburg and
Gotha.
This had been established in 1901 following
the succession of King Edward VII, bringing
the House of Hanover which had ruled Britain
for nearly two centuries to an end.
However, the House of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha
name, which was assigned on account of the
extensive links between the British royal
family and many of the most senior royal lines
within Germany, became problematic in the
context of the First World War.
It reminded far too many people that the royals
had extensive amounts of German blood and
indeed George V was the first cousin of the
German Kaiser, Wilhelm II.
In particular when the Germans began dropping
bombs on London in 1917 from planes named